this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
or / software this is Robert for
software engineering radio today I am
joined by Martin Thompson Martin
Thompson is one of the leading experts
in the field of computer system
performance and tuning he's a frequent
speaker at technology conferences the
founder of Lmax
a high-frequency trading firm he is one
of the founders of the open-source
disruptor project and he maintains the
blog mechanical sympathy he's currently
the proprietor of real logic limited a
computer systems performance consultancy
based in London Martin welcome to
software engineering radio hi Robert how
you doing today very well thank you
Martin please tell the listeners a
little bit about your background and how
you got interested in performance oh
it's kind of interesting I've done many
different things in his career stony
back a few decades but kind of
interestingly I always seem to get
dragged into earlier zwo by a computer
performance improves in an area new
opportunities are opened that just
weren't possible before I mean fact the
very first thing I did in this sort of
space was back in but 92 were I was
taking feeds from the Tron Stock
Exchange and at that time we were having
to process everything on IBM mainframes
but the feeds at that stage could
actually fit on to two hard disks if you
installed them into a PC when hard disks
at that stage were burned by 250
megabytes so think to Derek we've got
caches that are sort of starting to come
up into that sort of space but yeah we
could get did into that and we could
open up new opportunities for businesses
could do things that they just couldn't
do before my kind of career has gone on
through many different things through
sort of modeling of vehicles dealing
with large catalogs dealing with trading
systems very different demands but care
with performance
and high-throughput beam an underlined
feature through most of it and kind of
hard core computer science which is good
fun to do for a living the name of your
blog is mechanical sympathy what do you
mean by that
in the chemical sympathy is an
interesting name I'm also a big fan of
motor racing and the term comes from a
racing driver called Jackie Stewart who
the 1960s and 70s was an incredibly
successful racing driver and he
particularly was incredibly smooth and
very good in the wet and he talked about
having mechanical sympathy for the
vehicle he was driving when he showed
mechanical sympathy for that vehicle he
getting much more out of than other
drivers and this is where particularly
in the wet it showed very well where you
know where the limits are you push up to
the limits but not beyond the limits so
you get the best out of it and for him
it was about working in harmony with the
vehicle for me it's kind of similar with
software and hardware whenever software
shows in the chemical sympathy for how
the hardware and platform works it works
in harmony with it and you get the best
out of it too much software you see
today works against the underlying
hardware with very limited understanding
of it and as a result not just performs
poorly can also have robustness issues
whereby things are just not used
correctly in ads conditions pop up and
things start to go wrong this doesn't
mean you need to understand things in my
new detail or be an absolute expert is
about understanding what is important
and distilling the essence of what is
important when using the underlying
hardware to understand the basic
characteristics
just like in motor racing if I need to
drive a very fast car I don't need to
know how to rebuild an engine but I
didn't know how it works I need to
understand how the basics of a gearbox
works or the basics of suspension works
by understanding that at a fundamental
level I can then get the best out of it
similar applies to software could you
give us an overview of the basic
computer hardware that you think are
poorly understood by a lot of software
developers yeah there's lots of great
examples of this and a lot of it is
actually naming conventions that we use
in this space which actually leads
people along where the names we choose
things are very very important than the
program's people's interaction like for
example we
but random access memory yet access to
memory is not random at all
there's orders of magnitude difference
between whether you access memory
sequentially and whether you access it
completely random because of how the
hardware works it takes a number of
deaths and those things to Nick namely
much lower latency so it hides the
latency to me in memory and how we
access stuff now I go through memory
sequentially it can almost completely
hide that and we can be accessing memory
of what effectively looks like less than
a nanosecond on a modern PC if I start
accessing it completely random and this
is without even building of queues
inside our infrastructure we're looking
at anywhere from sort of 70 to over a
hundred nanoseconds for access so to see
and then we're on the same machine but
just with a different access pattern so
what this suggests is in fact that
memory be here it's very much like a
serial device more like teeth than those
around an access device and how we
access our disks are could very similar
characteristics even SSDs have similar
characteristics but most people are not
aware of these things and they just will
access the underlying memory subsystem
with very little understanding for how
it actually works
and as a result get performance issues
in reading through some of your blog
posts there's a consistent theme of the
extent to which program performance is
dominated by the relationship between
the CPU cores and the layers of CPU
caching talk a little bit about the
importance of that yeah that's something
that very much does jump out when you
start monitoring and profiling modern
software we have very small caches
organized into a cache hierarchy of
ever-increasing sizes but also
ever-increasing latency so for example
your CPU doesn't actually work on your
memory it never does it loads that
memory into internal registers performs
operations on those registers and in
stores that memory back out again it
doesn't store that memory directly to
the in memory its doors it to the cache
subsystem Casso system is the source of
truth in our modern computer systems and
there spill back to me and memory
whenever the cache subsystems have
reached the point of exhaustion so the
follower least recently used type
algorithm were I we end up pulling in
data and data that used recently will be
hot and
that's a useful thing doesn't want to
advances memory that is used recently is
likely to be there so the temporal type
bet they also pull memory and in chunks
it doesn't pull them in and that
survives oppose remaining cache lines or
in pages depend on which layer of the
cash flow system we're dealing with so
memory that's close together
tends to benefit from being pulled in
together and then it also takes a third
bed on patterns of access we have
Hardware be Esprit factors in our cache
subsystem that are looking for patterns
of access through our code and based on
those patterns of access will actually
prefect the memory into those caches l1
caches were the process is working
directly with its only three to four
cycles to access that so you're looking
at this is one nanosecond type period to
access that you go to the l2 which is a
larger cache cigano from a 32k cache to
a 256 care cache on a modern intel
processor definite ear l3 which is
anywhere between sort of 2 and 30
megabytes depending on what model you
bought and there's ice extent that get
bigger but also higher latency and how
we get them now when this starts the
matter is the algorithms we choose we're
taught computer science in school and we
learn about the order of algorithms but
the order of the algorithms does not
take into account the underlying
hardware like a good example being a
linked list if I want to walk a linked
list it should be the same order of
algorithm for the linked list versus and
are where it doesn't say it's going to
be significantly more I look at the
order of the algorithm it is a different
order for algorithms I want to randomly
access any given element and a rare has
got order one for any random element and
it will be an order and with a linked
list what's much more significant is if
I start walking a linked list
linked lists are implemented as nodes
with pointers off to the elements that
are held in that list those could be
anywhere around the blend memory
depending on where that memory has been
allocated and as a result you've got a
random access pattern namely quad where
pre-factors can help us the fact that D
that that is co-located gets taken
together gamma doesn't help us and the
temporal side doesn't help some less we
happen to just access that data very
very recently so they can be as much as
an order of magnitude difference dealing
with a large red versus a large length
list and how
access these things these patterns also
continue through things like maps and
trees and office of other structures and
now we have the aware of what those
units of access but the data currency is
when we deal with data as we move in and
out of our CPUs to manipulate it but I
think you're saying is the hardware
architecture makes certain bets about
how programs going to access memory and
it would make sense for programmers to
program in such a way that their bets
will be right most of the time yes that
is correct
so there's so many bats at the hardware
max is good three bets I talked about
the the fact that it's kind of a stat
there's also the spatial that there's a
pattern based bet that's taken care of
there's always more and more silicon and
intelligence keeps getting invested in
making that better because so far it can
fundamentally go if you completely
randomly access your memory other
results you will get the pros possible
performance because the hardware kind of
help you out that in fact goes brother
it's not just your do this also your
instruction stream so our processors are
also taking bets on branches and however
when we predicted modern processors
speculated on which we're branches going
to go because it may not have to did it
yet so waffles waiting on a cache
minister retrieved either but it's going
to make a decision on the next branch in
your code and can actually make an
assumption that's true or false and
proceed executing more instructions if
it later finds out that that was wrong
it has to throw everything away if it
turns out that that was right it's
already needed progress and the bat has
paired off so our code can be faster and
then that comes down to well if it's
keeping statistics on your branches in
your code your code needs to be
predictable it needs to follow similar
so it's so passive it's very random it's
going to lose out on that it's
predictable
it won't the interesting thing is many
branches in code can quite often be
replaced by mathematics when you think
about the algorithms and how they can be
applied or even just getting back to a
cleaner understanding of the demand
model there's a lot about high modern
processors and runtimes work but if you
want really good performance you want to
have small clean quite linear methods
that are very composed
of large methods with lots of branching
lots of looping or incredibly hard to
optimize from CPU level the OS level
runtime level right up through our
stacks so sort of clean very predictable
code runs incredibly fast it's also very
easy per humans to read and reason about
so they're not at odds with each other
I quite often hear people saying Albert
if i optimize my code and i designed for
high performance it will be readable i
find that that is literally not trillion
in fact it's quite the opposite nice
sort of clean elegant methods well
decoupled high cohesion nice and simple
and composable in fact performs
incredibly well for time 90% of the use
cases that they'll actually apply to
give to edge conditions where you have
to do something a little bit specific
but that's much more the exception than
the rule a moment ago martin you were
talking about arrays versus a list i ran
across one of your blog posts in which
you suggest that a lot of the standard
libraries in common programming
languages are not very machine friendly
in their basic data structures is that
the case that's very much the kiss so
the most popular language in the world
java for example if i want to lay out an
array of structures and a really good
example of why i want to do that is i'm
i want to implement a much better
implementation of a hash map inside java
i have to have an array of references
those array of references then point to
nodes that hold the beginning of the
chain for each chain for a range even
bucket inside the hash map it would be
much more efficient if i could lay out a
contiguous array of structures that are
the start up those buckets i remove the
stamp indirection and i have got a nice
striding this pattern for how to get to
those first level structures right
through if i need to probe forward these
are the things are not built into the
standard jetty care is written in a way
that is perfectly designed to cache miss
almost constantly if you take an extreme
difference the dictionary implementation
in c-sharp is implemented with a very
memory friendly layout and for data sets
out measure that to gigabytes losses at
least ten times faster to use the layout
of the dictionary and add verses the
hash mark and java and there's lots of
other examples without even needing
massive changes in java most of the time
we key into different data structures
based on primitives so it may be and
long or it may be an INT or some other
very simple key be a system to get into
it if we use open addressing and linear
probing style hash maps from there again
we can get nearly an order of magnitude
improvement in performance where we hash
directly to application and we probe
forward we're walking through memory and
a nice brown we moderns all let out in
and a rare for how to access that
there's only one of a number of examples
I could go on with trees for example
people implement binary trees where we
should be implementing n where trees
where we're pulling in blocks that have
a number of nodes to a number of
children the same sort of techniques
that we used to apply on disks when
developing databases we should be doing
the same thing in memory under data
structures a lot of our data structures
that we're using in common languages are
not designed with this thinking even
goes further and the guys who developed
the collections libraries and Java have
comments in the source code that you can
go in and read where there's constants
in the code for different factors and
the comments next to them says like
these factors should be revisited on a
regular occurrence and updated based
upon new measurement since those were
created many many years ago to my knows
they've never even been updated once Wow
I have another library related question
in one of your talks at two konzern
Francisco you are talking about
performance tuning you were emphasizing
the very high cost of multiple rounds of
copying that performance is often
dominated by a third-party library like
a JDBC or Message Queuing from a vendor
which is doing multiple unnecessary
copies what do you do when you're
building a system and your bottleneck is
in a third-party library that's an
interesting challenge ideally you can
get an alternative to that library but
that's not always the case I think a lot
of libraries are designed almost as an
afterthought
I think JDBC is a very good example of
this they have been improving over time
but still like for example we still
don't have
blocking JDBC libraries that are
synchronous we should have that only
don't have that in our current designs
but when I've looked into them in the
past us you see the way the codes been
written is always being written by
multiple teams where buffers are harmed
at all from layer to layer to layer to
layer and as a result is very
inefficient sometimes these patterns
have been copied from see where some of
these patterns are much more efficient
with a handing off a pointer in jail but
it's quite often not the case because a
lot of code is not designed to work
within subsets or for res then a copying
near wrap over and over again you see
this quite often because even if you
don't have the source code and I think
about Java is the bytecode Leedy compile
that can also be profiled and you can
see these issues that do exist on a
number of cases I've had to decompile
libraries and put fixes in and try to
submit them back to the vendors or
actually come up with completely
alternative client implementations
provide the bottleneck and the library
was so significant at building a version
of my client library was actually the
cost-effective way to get our system to
scale and perform I'd like to talk a bit
about multi-core computing there's a
well known I'm not sure if this is a
paper or a quote stating the free lunch
is over
what did the guy who said that mean I
think you're referring to herb Sutter's
famous essay
I had learned about 2007 2008 what herb
was pointing out at that point is that
we reached the point where by us we're
shrinking the manufacturing process and
the thermal densities are going up so
high that we can keep increasing clock
speed so for a number of years we have
been having this free lunch offer every
18 months
our CPUs are effectively doubling in
performance because of the doubling of
clock speed as we improve the
manufacturing process but we've hit a
wall with that and it seems incredibly
difficult to get CPUs to clot much more
than four gigahertz without having
serious thermal issues we can't
dissipate the heat so CPUs are getting
faster so the kind of there is an
interesting point that since they and
CPUs have not been getting about the
rates that we're getting faster if they
are getting faster but the width at
which they're getting faster has
significantly slowed down since that
point and that's because clock speed is
staying largely the same processors are
getting smarter but more interesting is
actually
cache subsystems are getting smarter to
processes themselves quite often are not
a limitation in our systems if you
measure most systems you'll see that
your processors are idle most of the
times it is not be instead data fast
enough and that's where the real action
is the real action is how do we feed
data and instructions into our processes
fast enough to actually execute them and
that's where the memory subsystems are
coming into class or understanding that
we have a hierarchical memory subsystem
we have an memory subsystem neither it's
even gone non-uniform and how it works
so you'll hear the term Numa non-uniform
memory architecture I quite often see
this as an issue with people by a multi
node server and they don't realize that
memory is connected to individual nodes
within that server even the very simple
and you've got a two node server where
there's a socket that has got memory
connected to it you've got another
socket in the same machine with memory
connected to it and those two sockets
are connected by a high speed
interconnect or traversal across that
interconnect is 20 nanoseconds each way
so a lone trip is an additional 40
nanoseconds so if I'm accessing memory
from one CPU socket that's connected to
the other CPU socket I'm not in 40
nanoseconds to everything it doesn't
matter whether it's in the cache
subsystem or the memory subsystem of the
other socket
I still got at 40 nanoseconds added on
as an additional cost quite often you
can get a huge speed-up in systems just
by using some OS level binding the cell
cap I want to run my program be at a JVM
or C program or anything else I have
sufficiently and wait and sufficient
cores to run all my threads that need to
run on a single one of those sockets
with a single memory region it can in
fact be up to three times faster then
spread across both room which the
operating system will do by default and
people don't seem to your work that one
of the things I find quite shocking is
now that you can go to somewhere like
Dowell site and then the past if you
wanted to buy a large memory system or a
large at core current system you went
through the channel and you dealt with a
provider like so Narada more HP and the
person takes managing the channel would
have a sensible conversation with you
but what software do you need what
hardware do you need what's the usage
you're going to be making sure you
purchase the right
what we start seeing now is people can
self-service you can go onto the Dell
website and you can click on the boxes
that you want and get something
delivered the problem is people just
think more is better so they'll have
extra sockets extra memory extra things
inside this machine the main choose not
to have a two socket machine then they
have a four socket or an its socket
machine where some of these Numa facts
start to get magnified even more so the
trips between the nodes can be one two
or three jumps even between the nodes
and the mesh it's in there which adds
significantly more latency to all
accesses to memory which then really
hurts performance and so as a result of
spending more money on hardware software
actually slows down understood to that
lack of mechanical sympathy for the
hardware in which they're running would
it be fair to say that most systems are
not getting in course of performance out
of an end car machine I think that is
very for if you actually measure in
those systems you'll find that a lot of
the cores or are just sitting idle most
of the time and even more so you start
getting interesting the facts work maybe
one or two colors are running a hundred
percent and the rest are sitting idle
because there's a contention point in
the design of the software and that
contention point means that everything
else is bottlenecking and going through
that that's where things like harm
dollars law and littles law kick in and
you're trying to model what's going on
in the software that can be even further
than just the software itself it can be
the wrong time for example if you're
going to know on something like a Java
Runtime and you're allocating also
memory and the garbage collector needs
to come in this times where all the
threads have to be brought to save point
to allow the garbage collector to
continue bringing all those threads to
see a point means there's no progress
been made on those threads and you'll
find that you've got lots of island
colors and when you bring all threads to
see a point you may get hundred threads
to see a point incredibly quickly and
one thread may take a long time to come
see a point because it's doing something
like a memory copy or allocation of a
large array or a large clone of an
object and everything has to wait for it
to complete you don't make progress on
those other 99 you have to wait for all
hundred to reach that point including
this low running thread to come to say a
point and band progresses made or
whatever the JVM is going to do like
going to do garbage collection
is going to do class or loading or
optimization or lochley biasing there's
lots of things that can be going on
inside our DBMS at that point in time
it's not just job that can help them
across many other material times in fact
other management translates to maybe PHP
or other sort of things that tighten or
actually even last well designed for
scaling up to incredibly high codes
because they haven't thought about in
advance to do that and so we get
limitations where was bottlenecks in the
code bottlenecks in the room time and as
a result things are serializing on those
bottlenecks and northing else is making
progress you just brought off the JVM
and I would like to come back to that
but first I'd like you to discuss these
two core concepts of system throughput
and Dahl's law and littles law which you
just mentioned
yeah the did - I think should be bread
and butter understanding from those
people who are working on large systems
or systems with any performance needs it
and even moderate performance needs um
does law does a very nice to almost
describing the limitation in which you
can scale up any algorithm by adding
extra cores to the problem so for
example if my algorithm is 95% Paul out
that got 5% of it that must happen
sequentially you can throw more than
about 20 colors out of it and with it
you just field getting more speed up and
it's also awesome topically approaching
that so your skill up is fundamentally
limited because you end up with as many
cores as she throw out it weeding on
that 5% and then that starts to magnify
up with the number of threads that you
throw the problem and available colors
its careful as I mean just watching how
quickly it comes and gets you as we've
been through dealing with two core
machines and for corn even going to your
core most of this has been reasonably
hidden but it starts getting big and
ugly very quickly as you start
approaching 16 32 64 colors well I kind
of like to look at it in algorithms like
if you have a serialization point you
can't run from around all a will hunt
you down and your algorithm will be
fundamentally limited in how much they
can scale even a single-digit percentage
points for any part of an algorithm
that's required to be serial
across all of the different routes and
so much requires being serial and people
can even just miss it on simple things
like having a cash in their software
where the cash has got a lock around
mutations to that lots of mutations
going on everything is no serializing on
the cashion they think they're actually
improved in performance but there could
be massively hurting performance it's
kind of um dolls law and how it
describes the serializing component and
what potential speed ups you can get the
one that works nicely hand in home if it
is littles law which describes the
queuing theory that happens around
points of serialization so as soon as
you've got a point of serialization in
your code only one thing can use it as a
time as a result you can form and with
queues bowling in your system you've got
to see your impact on latency because
the cue forms your latency grows as a
result of your cues on bounders your
system can just get ever-increasingly
indices and then it actually gets worse
after a while because you start using up
all of your memory especially when you
have unbounded queues in your system
behind the twos or everywhere whether
people realize that or not if you have a
lot of assembler for anything like that
people think they don't have a queue or
guess what happens to everything waiting
on getting that locked resource or
resource protected by some sort of
critical section this damn was queue and
those kids are on bounded and unbounded
queues can just grow unchecked at that
point what happens whenever there don't
any longer fit inside the cache
subsystem you write to me and then later
on or at least recently used algorithm
the person that was struggling the
keyboard with consuming is no hit the
cache misses on top of it another result
your system very quickly dies a good
belief in that if you have unbounded
queues in your system you've just got a
crash waiting to happen and it's going
to happen where we least want it one of
the themes in your writing and blogging
is the extent to which multi-threaded
program performance is often dominated
by the cost of coordination and
switching rather than doing actual work
which is what you want it to do
why do you the best intention programs
end up so badly when you go to multiple
threads I think it's because of the
change in hardware and high systems have
been developed we've been typically
running or on uniprocessor systems for a
long time even a lot of current
developers have been working on you
sesor systems wouldn't have cut their
teeth and now we've gone multi-core for
example I was on a uniprocessor system
running Java code the JVM will actually
remove all locks from the code because
you don't actually need them in the case
of uniprocessors system because you'll
never have enough thread heading that
did at the same time you'll be time
sliced until the point where not the
thread runs now in a world of true
multi-core we're having to genuinely
apply locks and memory buyers and have
mutual exclusion applied and one of the
problems with all of this is signaling
to other threads when something's done
simple example of this is if I want to
offer to a queue and tag from the queue
so if I going to tag from the queue in
the queue is empty without going to
block in tag from thank you I have to go
asleep so and calling into the operating
system and asking to have my thread
suspended at that point whenever I go to
offer something to the queue at that
point what happens is the thread that
goes offered to the tooth has to let the
operating system note there's something
now in not to and to wake up that other
thread that whole housekeeping of having
to wake up that of the thread and signal
via the operating system is incredibly
high cost on a modern operating system
that can be anywhere between about 3 and
15 to 16 microseconds to carry out
operation as often we're more processing
cycles and it actually requires to do
the business project at setting around
that so the design of sort of making
things multi-threaded and having locks
and condition variables turned off
between stages can quite often really
impact the performance of the software
where you'd be better off just writing a
single threaded one of the things I try
to encourage people to do is actually
see if you can get your business logic
to run on a single thread and quite
often you can and it's efficient to run
at that stage the problem is you can't
be making blocking calls but a lot of
people design software that is
synchronous and makes blocking calls as
a result you can't run it on a single
thread and you can't scale up so you
need to move to a more event based
pattern and make known blocking calls
and then you can have effectively single
threads of execution running without all
the headaches of concurrency and the
performance don't
that comes with that you are one of the
contributors to an open-source project
called disrupter which does embody some
of these concepts that you're describing
would you tell us a bit about the
thinking behind the disrupter and how it
solves some of these problems sure some
of the things I've done in the past is
working on high performance gaming sites
and financial exchanges now one of the
challenges in those environments is
incredibly high throughput like
literally into the tens and hundreds of
thousands of operations per seconds that
need to occur but combined with that is
a need for very low and predictable
latency so what you need to do is get
that throughput to happen with the low
latency and also with is lower jitter as
possible and in doing that we looked at
many different designs and the disrupter
Kim I drafted but a number of natural
design pressures pushing design insert
interaction wasn't the case of let's sit
down and dream up the disrupter is a
case of look at the requirements look at
the natural design pressures that we
were having imposed upon us and how do
we evolve our design to meet those
design pressures and so it evolved out
of that and so whenever we were building
exchanges number things you try to do is
to make it incredibly resilient so to
make something resilient you need to be
saving data to disk you need to be
replicating it to other nodes you also
need to be on marshalling that data is
coming in and off the wire and need to
be doing the business logic and
repeating that all on the way out or a
lot of those things can run completely
independently as long as they're
synchronized and you're not synchronize
going to lock sense but synchronized in
a claiming sense at the right point in
time so for example I can be writing
entries to disk wealth by replicating
those entries to another node earn a
number of other nodes what I'm also on
marceline that data getting it ready to
be invoked by the business logic as I'm
processing stuff I want to do that as
fast as possible with the minimum
overhead so the design of the disrupter
is gained based on mechanical sympathy
so how can I run all of those threads in
parallel
how can I have a really low cost
coordination that keeps everything in
step and let each that's each of the
other threads
when different points have been reached
and that's all done using concepts known
as lock for your algorithms and how it
works it's also designed to take garbage
collection pressure off the JVM because
if you want a very low jitter
environment you don't want to be
allocating a lot of garbage because a
lot of garbage then means garbage
collection cycles and with many of the
current VMs that are out there they have
issues with doing concurrent collections
and that their fallback to stop the
world pauses that cause your application
as well as everything else is hardening
and then as a result you can't respond
and have low latency so the designers
disrupters to pre-allocated all of the
initial data you have a name just reuse
it over and over again in large ring
buffers to prompt data through the
system and as a result you can build
very high throughput very low latency
systems with the proviso that you always
have enough cores to run threads that
want to run the feed look yes I see with
people using the disrupter is they try
to run where more threads than they have
colors available and in that case it's
not the sweet spot for these two
disruptors so if you've got a 16 core
system but you want to run 100 threads
it's not designed to run well in that
scenario if you have a 16 core system
and you've got 10 threads that need to
run concurrently it can do incredibly
well and give you very good throughput
Martyn wire ring buffer the ring buffer
is interesting because of mechanical
sympathy thing so with a ring buffer you
go around it reusing it over and over
again I mentioned earlier that our
hardware takes bets on things like
recently news data and have been
predictable access as I go run a ring
offer I've got predictable access to
memory so the hardware prefetcher can be
playing that memory in and making it
available to me so it's in there as I go
to use it
also as I hand off from producer to
consumer it's hot in the caches and can
be moved between them very effectively
it's a technique that's used within most
hardware part of the interesting side of
studying hardware is you learn a lot of
things about data structures that work
incredibly well that also work very well
in software so if you look at how most
network cards most drivers of most
descriptions that are designed they all
use ring buffers internally get modern
software very often does not use ring
another concept you mentioned a moment
ago that is a common theme in your
writing is the lock-free algorithms tell
us what lock-free is and why does it
matter yes so as I mentioned before
whenever I'm sort of entering a critical
faction between two threads to mutate
some data or I want to signal from one
thread to another that a change has
occurred that is typically done with a
lock for the critical section on a
condition variable to signal the change
that's going on the condition variable
mesh you up as a weird notified per and
jela and they show up as a signal and
then a weird statement in Java if using
Java util concurrent abusing POSIX it
will be new taxes and condition
variables that on the hood but they're
all basically mal contains a fundamental
structure or something that provides a
critical faction and something that does
the signaling whenever this is to happen
if your lock is ever contended and when
you need a signal via the condition
variable you have to get the kernel
involved so you end up calling into the
operating system kernel to get that
happen that's a very high overhead
process I like to think of it it's like
asking the government to get involved or
asking the lawyers to come and help you
make a decision it works
it's see if it's a fact of but it's
incredibly high cost those operations
end up costing millions of cycles in how
they actually end up executing the other
side of it is with lock-free algorithms
is you decide not to get a third party
involved what you do is you greet a set
of coordination steps between threads
that are coordinating and their signal
change by making memory visible in a
predefined order and for that you need
to take control over the ordering them
which changes half in a particular
points of an algorithm so that can be
seen so we think of you and I want to
interact on a task I can work on part of
the tasks you can work on part of the
task and we can agree points at which we
will share and interact
we just need to agree with the protocol
for that is and make those points of the
protocol visible to each other lochley
algorithms allow us to do that so within
user space in a program different
threads can communicate without getting
the kernel involved by applying a number
of techniques this technique so
typically how do I make memory visible
in a certain order because our compilers
and our process
we'll try to do lots of things out of
order to get more performance as long as
the illusion of any given thread looks
like it happens in the order of your
program it doesn't need to happen in
order to a program the good example
would be if I have a loop and inside
that loop I do some modifications to
some theater some calculations but I
also need to implement my lid cutter
does it matter if I increment the loop
counter at the beginning of the loop in
the middle of the loop or a band of the
loop as well as it's done by the time I
didn't go around and check again that's
all that matters
and our compilers under our CPS will
reorder to get us performance to make
that happen
these are the things start to matter
between threads because if the
visibility changes in order and I I've
got a problem coordinating with another
thread so I need to put hints into my
coding hence directives to say certain
things must happen in a certain order
when they're visible to another thread
and so that's one part of is getting
that whole memory ordering and
visibility crud I think that's the most
important point the next most important
point out to that is certain operations
need to happen atomically and there can
be a multi-step operation so for example
and they want to try something on may
feel so I may want to increment the
counter so nice ignoring that my work is
done I'm going to do that by increment
in a counter if multiple threads can
increment that country you can get a
lost object like one thread rated with
value 10 another one reads it with value
10 they both can increment try to set
the value to 11 both succeed and as a
result one of those increments is lost
what you need to do to overcome that is
use techniques what are known as cars
components that are components Rob
techniques whereby I will conditionally
update that counter if it's an estate
that I know so they'll be case of like I
read the variable it's 10 I do an
increment and I could write it to be 11
but I'll write it to the 11 conditional
on it being tan if it's not 10 I'll feel
and I can go around and try again and so
lottery algorithms about those two major
things is making sure all the things
happen in the correct order and certain
things happen atomically so a
coordination can happen or those two
basic things you can build up most
algorithms to have coordination if it's
multi-step you just build it as a state
machine we do one step then another
stepped in another step just like we
would do in real life several times
you've brought up the issue of Java
garbage collection do you feel that the
evolution of most programming languages
from malloc and free to garbage
collection has been an improvement or a
mixed blessing it's an interesting one
so if you have very specific use cases
you can usually take control memory
allocation and reclamation yourself much
more efficiently than any
general-purpose
edie means of memory management so a
good example of this is actually using a
ring buffer to exchange memory from a
producer to a consumer but a lot of
things don't have that in fact it can
actually be quite tricky what if you've
got multiple producers multiple
consumers or you handoff things to other
threads so in a multi-threaded
environment managing memory is
incredibly tricky people say ok well
I'll use reference counting but
reference counting then needs to use
those cows there's techniques that I've
just been talking about which are
actually very expensive and so hungee
memory around in a multi-threaded
environment using reference counting is
probably one of the slowest means by
which you can do that garbage collectors
take away a lot of that problem by
collecting concurrently and vegies in
tracing these garbage collectors they're
finding things that are reachable and
removing that takes away a whole class
of bugs I've done a lot of programming
in low-level languages and higher-level
languages that have garbage collection
and when you get garbage collection is
definitely Tech's play a class of bugs
that you just don't have to worry about
anymore it's just access to memory on
the whole so having things like bones
checking and range checking and
different things that are useful gets
rid of a class of bugs that you
generally don't catch in languages like
C but it usually has a cost what's
fascinating from the about this subject
is theoretically a garbage collector can
be doing most efficient general-purpose
way of allocating and reclaiming memory
a truly concurrent generational garbage
collector when you're able to allocate
sufficient memory to the problem can
beat pretty much any other
general-purpose
allocation reclamation model the problem
is most of our garbage collectors are
written with quite simplistic views
around how we collect in particular and
that they expect the world to be stopped
to do certain phases of the class
by stopping to do certain phases of the
collection there's parts of that cycle
ends up having a serial component which
has Allen dolls law involved so it stops
us killing up and it also causes nasty
pauses in our algorithms as they execute
there are collectors out there that are
truly concurrent with our code and give
us incredible efficiency of allocation
reclamation one good example is the
seafood collector from the zoo but it's
the only one that I know that's
commercially available I can give us
those sorts of very high throughput
rates and collection rates and be very
easy to use without pauses given ambleve
law is their inherent limit on the
number of cores that a JVM can use
effectively if their entire rest of the
program did not have any bottlenecks it
seems to depend on how much allocation
you've got what other things are going
on so bringing threads to see a point is
one of the biggest issues within our
modern JM so there's a number of cases a
cause that to be a problem so if spring
interest to see a point is that if I
want to do anything that involves to
stop the world pause the first thing I
must do before I do that work is bring
all threads the CF point at which point
I've noticed out the world so I could be
doing a garbage collection cycle I could
be doing class on loading I could be
doing the optimization I could be doing
lockrey Bassam is that there's a number
of things that can be helping Evangelion
but I need to bring all of those threads
to see if point-first
that is a serial problem so I think one
of the most important things with the
new JVM is we've got to have things AI
do not happen under save point so that
they don't need to start the world pause
there are truly concurrent I think
that's one major step
the other major stamp that we need to
have is even when we do need to use CF
points we need to go around checking all
parts inside the JVM we've got a long
path in getting a thread to save point
because even if you've got one thing
that takes a long time to get the save
point it's going to hold everything else
back and as a result I'm dolls law is
kicking in at that point so there needs
to be significant time spent on time to
save point within the JVM that add to
this point a really good where to
highlight it is a lot of people measure
the garbage collection time in their
applications one flag that should be
turned on is application stop time
and you'll often find that application
stop time is significantly greater than
the time to do the garbage collection
that is because you needed to bring all
of those dreads to save point and as you
usually what the component of the time
is I quite often find in measuring
systems that bringing drugs to see a
point is greater than the actual work
being done mix every data phase of
garbage collection Wow
so to what extent have you seen that the
performance of Java server programs can
be substantially improved by tuning the
various garbage collection switches and
parameters you can see it opening quite
a lot
there's committed two classes of
problems I could often see here one is
someone has actually gone about tuning
it and they've done more harm than good
and it would've been better off leaving
the system with defaults unlimited to
put in tuning parameters that were based
upon a behavior that was seen in an old
version of a JVM and the cap those
tuning parameters and they've gone
through a number of upgrades and they're
not handing points where some of those
configuration options to put in are
harmful rather than helpful the other
side is quite often the case that people
have just miss configured for the basics
of what's going on so that they haven't
profiled or application to see how much
heap do I need what side of
new-generation do I need what size the
survivor generations donate what size of
old generation do I need and just by
sizing things correctly these two porn
live data sets and what you're seeing in
promotion rates to avoid that can have
massive impacts on just improving how
your application runs but is it taking
the time to do that the biggest
challenge with most of this I find is
most people don't have representative
tests to actually run in a performance
environment they're just trying to react
to problems they're seeing in live
systems they don't have very good
monitoring on their live systems and
penny and they've got nowhere for
creating what's been happening on their
live systems as a result they just come
tuned and they're just blind blind and
making gases and then goes that's one of
the biggest problems I see with the
systems not being designed to perform
and do well is people just don't have a
performance environment in suitable
pasts what are some of the key things
that systems should be monitoring with a
view toward using garbage collection
smarter
turn on god's klaxon logging I think
it's a key point I've written a blog
article on garbage collection distilled
there's a goal for those blog articles
to give people an overview of what are
the basic types of collectors to come
within JVM and one of the basic tuning
parameters that are in there and also
Dan is that I've given some for the
minimal flag that should be turned on so
you get logging off the right
information once that information is
there you can then input it into certain
tools and it's very low overhead on a
production system you can turn on
garbage collection logging it generally
most people won't even notice it is
turned on and from there you can then
take the results of those logs put them
into a tool and analyze them and see
what's happening to your application you
spoke earlier about the inability in the
java language to define an array of
records rather than an array of
references and some of your talks you
mentioned the concept of off heap
structures to get around this could you
tell us a bit more about that yes so to
get predictable memory layout means that
we can then get predictable performance
from our memory subsystems and so the
languages need to give us the ability to
do this I don't think it's a feature
that everyday developers need to use but
I think it's particularly very important
for library designers so we should be
able design mounts trees all sorts of
other collections that internally are
well designed for memory usage and given
those good memory performance
unfortunately Java as a language and the
bytecode that's underneath that doesn't
have the expressiveness to let us layout
memory as we need to I think there's
three major cases where we need to have
control over memory led one is to be
able to load an array of structures or
unwrapped objects so that I can stride
through those and avoid the interactions
or by dead reckoning I can go to any
given structure without a dereference
and step to get to there because each
dereference step with the cache miss can
be a hundred nanoseconds on into your
cost or it should be just dead racking
go to that check and then I should have
a walk forward from a from a point with
predictable stride and as a result avoid
all of that I should go do similar
things in having a bore
oh I know that's an n-word tree a second
baby star trees of any description and
doodles efficiently those will be the
things that underlie our basic
collections and by having those features
we can then build a much more efficient
collections so that's point one has been
able to lay out of memory as an array of
structures second point on this what we
need is we need to sometimes inline or
cluster one object into another and a
good example of this is there have a cue
structure and I've got a head and a tail
why they want to be reference off to an
object that contains the head or the
tail descriptor I want to have that in
line and reach it by dad rattling as
well so again get rid of that
dereferencing so I should be able to
collapse small objects into large
objects the good examples of this is
like things like a atomic long atomic
end small objects that are wrappers
around a primitive type that should be
able to collapse back into an object and
lay that out very efficiently third
thing that I would like to be able to do
is be able to extend something
dynamically so this is very similar to
the concept of a see structure that has
a variable length around at the end of
that structure where that's very useful
it's for things like say the string
object the string object has got some
peels in there the settings at the
hashcode the length of the field or an
offset within that field and then you've
got the array of bytes that come after
that of the rare of characters that
represent the string itself why do we
need to have an object that represents
the string with the dereference off to
another object that represents the array
the array should just continue on
continuously at the end of that object
to give us about memory locality and to
deal with that again by dada reckoning
without the interaction offset JVM can
start playing some tricks for things
like string because it knows that string
is but I should build the design almost
any structure like that and make sure I
get a nice efficient layout in how it
works and I should move the design
libraries knowing that some of these
features exist they don't need to be
language changes it can be done with
simple intrinsics and some patterns that
are agreed in advance the JVM looks out
for and it applies the intrinsics based
upon those patterns in code just like
they do for all of the other intrinsic
sets during the code with these features
we can get
magnitude improvement in certain
collections and certain access patterns
how would you change computer science
education for undergraduates I would
focus a lot more on things like a
scientific method being part of the
education learning to work from reason
measurement and science we've got to be
fundamental just as you would get in a
science degree in any other subject
having it instilled I think sort of
learning about how to learn how to
reason how to keep up with a ever moving
subject material and being aware of
things that's very easy for humans to
fall into the populists approach and
follow fashion it would be nice to look
more the fact that things do move and
how do we keep up but how do we keep up
and know that approaches are solid and
signed because this is one thing we can
be certain off in our subject matter is
that it's going to be changing on a
phenomenal rate and if you would learn a
lot of specifics at university they're
going to be out of date incredibly
quickly so you need to be learning an
approach approach that's sustainable
over the long term and what are the
things that matter so then people talk
about Argyl I think it's important to
talk about things like feedback cycles
and what score in our jail is that you
design things so that your feedback
cycles are as short as possible the
short feedback cycles you make better
decisions in fact it's okay to get stuff
wrong if your feedback cycles are very
tight and you can very little waste you
can then make rapid progress and even
deal with failure on the whack but we
get only talks about standards and all
the ceremony around our jaw we don't
talk about fundamental principles that
underlie it and that's what's really
mattered other matters I believe and I
think we need to do that with computing
learning how things work learning how
things work from the ground up I think
in the modern world most people know I
graduated with the computer science
degree and they have never programmed in
a language that has any direct memory
access at all that's nice to be able to
abstract about that if you don't know
the fundamentals to how it works you're
just going to make bad decisions because
you just assume in this magic and we're
into the realms of witchcraft rather
than science Martin if listeners would
like to learn more about your ideas and
your
how should they do that my blog is one
point where people can start to look at
look at mechanical sympathy or you can
also go and join the mechanical sympathy
discussion group on Google where there's
some great chats that happen there will
we have people discussing a lot of these
subjects and digging into more detail
and kind of getting back to basics and
how things fundamentally work
are there any conference presentations
that are available on the web that you'd
like people to have a look at as various
things I've done and hopefully I'll do
more in the future so if you google for
my nails and presentations that are on
input - or yeah and some of the others
that are out there hopefully it gives a
starting point
how does describe to me that my blogs
are usually the start of a very good
wiki walk to get people exposed to new
concepts and they can go off and then
understand more from that point so I
like to introduce people to something
it's not that they're going to learn
everything they ever need to learn from
that one point but it will hopefully
start
that's glad that they'll follow on and
learn more from great well Martin
Thompson thank you so much for speaking
to software engineering radio oh thank
you for having me it's been a pleasure
[Music]
thanks for listening to s-see radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to support us you can
advertise se radio by clicking the Digg
reddit delicious or slash buttons on the
site or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so the other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
please see the website for details
thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]